I'm here to talk to you about a new way of doing journalism.
أنا هنا لأحدثكم عن طريقة جديدة للقيام بعمل الصحافة.
Some people call this "citizen journalism,"
بعض الناس يسميها "صحافة المواطنين"،
other people call it "collaborative journalism."
والبعض الآخر يسميها "الصحافة التعاونية".
But really, it kind of means this: for the journalists, people like me,
إلا أنها تعني التالي: بالنسبة للصحفيين، مثلي،
it means accepting that you can't know everything,
تعني الاعتراف بأنه لا يمكنك أن تعرف كل شيء،
and allowing other people, through technology,
وأن تعطي الفرصة لأشخاص آخرين، باستخدام التكنولوجيا،
to be your eyes and your ears.
بأن يكونوا عينيك وأذنيك.
And for people like you, for other members of the public,
وللأشخاص الآخرين مثلكم، أفراد من الجمهور،
it can mean not just being the passive consumers of news,
يمكن أن يعني أن لا نكون متلقين غير فاعلين للأخبار،
but also coproducing news.
بل المشاركة في صنع الأخبار.
And I believe this can be a really empowering process.
ويمكن أن تكون هذه عملية تمكين حقيقية.
It can enable ordinary people to hold powerful organizations to account.
تمكن أشخاص عاديين من محاسبة المنظمات الكبيرة.
So I'm going to explain this to you today with two cases,
لذا سأشرح هذا لكم اليوم من خلال قضيتين،
two stories that I've investigated.
قضيتين قمت بالتحقيق بهما.
And they both involve controversial deaths.
وكلاهما تحتوي على وفيات مثيرة للجدل.
And in both cases, the authorities put out an official version of events,
وفي كلتا القضيتين، قامت السلطات بإصدار رواية رسمية لما حدث،
which was somewhat misleading.
والتي كانت مخادعة بعض الشيء.
We were able to tell an alternative truth utilizing new technology,
تمكنا من طرح حقيقة مغايرة مستخدمين تكنولوجيا جديدة،
utilizing social media, particularly Twitter.
باستخدام وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي، وخاصة تويتر.
Essentially, what I'm talking about here is, as I said, citizen journalism.
أساساً، ما أتحدث عنه هنا كما قلت هي صحافة المواطنين.
So, to take the first case:
لذا، لنأخذ القضية الأولى:
this is Ian Tomlinson, the man in the foreground.
هذا هو (ايان توميسون)، الرجل في المقدمة.
He was a newspaper vendor from London,
كان بائع جرائد في لندن،
and on the 1st of April 2009, he died at the G20 protests in London.
وفي الأول من إبريل 2009، توفي في احتياجات مجموعة العشرين في لندن.
Now, he had been -- he wasn't a protester,
لم يكن متظاهراً،
he'd been trying to find his way home from work
كان يحاول أن يجد طريقة للعودة لمنزله بعد العمل
through the demonstrations.
من خلال المظاهرات.
But he didn't get home.
إلا أنه لم يصل إلى منزله.
He had an encounter with a man behind him,
وحدث تصادم بينه وبين الرجل الذي خلفه،
and as you can see, the man behind him has covered his face with a balaclava.
وكما ترون الرجل الذي بالخلف غطى وجهه بقناع.
And, in fact, he wasn't showing his badge numbers.
كما أنه لم يكن يظهر أرقام شارته.
But I can tell you now, he was PC Simon Harwood,
ولكن يمكنني أن أخبركم الآن، أن الرجل شرطي اسمه سيمون هاروود،
a police officer with London's Metropolitan Police Force.
ضابط شرطة، مع قوة الشرطة في العاصمة لندن.
In fact, he belonged to the elite territorial support group.
في الواقع كان ينتمي إلى قوات النخبة بالدعم الأرضي.
Now, moments after this image was shot, Harwood struck Tomlinson with a baton,
وبعد لحظة من التقاط هذه الصورة، قام هاررود بضرب توميسون بعصا،
and he pushed him to ground,
وأسقطه على الأرض،
and Tomlinson died moments later.
وبعد لحظات توفي توميسون.
But that wasn't the story the police wanted us to tell.
ولكن هذه لم تكن القصة التي أرادت الشرطة منا أن نرويها.
Initially, through official statements and off-the-record briefings,
في البداية من خلال البيانات الرسمية والإحاطات غير الرسمية،
they said that Ian Tomlinson had died of natural causes.
قالوا أن (ايان توميسون) مات نتيجة أسباب طبيعية.
They said that there had been no contact with the police,
قالوا أنه لم يحصل أي احتكاك مع الشرطة،
that there were no marks on his body.
ولم تكن هناك أي كدمات على جسمه.
In fact, they said that when police tried to resuscitate him,
في الواقع، قالوا إنه حين حاولت الشرطة إنعاشه وإسعافه،
the police medics were impeded from doing so,
لم يتمكن مسعفو الشرطة من القيام بذلك،
because protesters were throwing missiles, believed to be bottles, at police.
لأن المتظاهرين كانوا يلقون صواريخ يعتقد أنها زجاجات على الشرطة.
And the result of that were stories like this.
والنتيجة كانت قصص كهذه.
I show you this slide,
أريكم هذه الشريحة،
because this was the newspaper that Ian Tomlinson had been selling
لأن هذه هي الصحيفة التي كان يبيعها (ايان توميسون)
for 20 years of his life.
لمدة 20 سنة من حياته.
And if any news organization had an obligation
وإذا كانت هناك أي مؤسسة إخبارية لديها التزام
to properly forensically analyze what had been going on,
لتحليل ما جرى من منظور الطب الشرعي،
it was the Evening Standard newspaper.
فهي صحيفة (ذا إيفنينج) العادية.
But they, like everyone else -- including my news organization --
ولكنهم مثل أي مؤسسة أخرى بما في ذلك مؤسستي الإخبارية
were misled by the official version of events put out by police.
تم تضليلهم من قبل الرواية الرسمية للأحداث التي نشرتها الشرطة.
But you can see here,
ولكن يمكنك أن ترى هنا،
the bottles that were supposedly being thrown at police
الزجاجات التي يُفترض أنها كانت تُلقى على الشرطة
were turned into bricks
تحولت إلى قرميد
by the time they reached this edition of the newspaper.
في الوقت الذي وصلوا فيه إلى هذه الطبعة من الصحيفة.
So we were suspicious,
لذلك لم نكن على يقين،
and we wanted to see if there was more to the story.
وكنا نريد أن نرى إن كان هناك تفاصيل أخرى للقصة.
We needed to find those protesters you see in the image,
كنا بحاجة للعثور على المحتجين الموجودين في الصورة،
but, of course, they had vanished by the time we started investigating.
إلا أنهم اختفوا في الوقت الذي بدأنا فيه بالتحقيق.
So how do you find the witnesses?
إذن كيف تجد الشهود؟
This is, for me, where it got really interesting.
هنا بالنسبة لي، حصلت أشياء مثيرة للاهتمام حقًا.
We turned to the internet.
اتجهنا إلى الإنترنت.
This is Twitter; you've heard a lot about it today.
هذا هو تويتر، لقد سمعتم الكثير عنه اليوم.
Essentially, for me, when I began investigating this case,
أساسًا، بالنسبة لي، عندما بدأت التحقيق في هذه القضية،
I was completely new to this; I'd signed up two days earlier.
كنت حديث العهد تمامًا بهذا البرنامج الذي سجلت فيه قبل يومين.
I discovered that Twitter was a microblogging site.
اكتشفت أن تويتر عبارة عن موقع تدوين مصغر.
It enabled me to send out short, 140-character messages.
يمكنني من إرسال رسائل قصيرة تضم 140 حرفًا.
Also, an amazing search facility.
وهو أيضا وسيلة بحث رائعة.
But it was a social arena in which other people were gathering
وهو أيضا ساحة اجتماعية يمكن لأناس آخرين الاجتماع معا
with a common motive.
يشتركون في دافع مشترك.
And in this case, independently of journalists,
وفي هذه القضية، وبشكل مستقل عن الصحفيين،
people themselves were interrogating exactly what had happened to Ian Tomlinson
كان الناس بأنفسهم يتساءلون عن ماذا حدث بالضبط لـ(ايان توميسون)
in his last 30 minutes of life.
في آخر 30 دقيقة من حياته.
Individuals like these two guys.
أشخاص مثل هذين الرجلين.
They went to Ian Tomlinson's aid after he collapsed.
ذهبوا لمساعدة (ايان توميسون) بعد أن وقع أرضا.
They phoned the ambulance.
اتصلوا بالإسعاف.
They didn't see any bottles, they didn't see any bricks.
لم يروا أي زجاجات، ولم يروا أي قرميد.
So they were concerned that the stories weren't quite as accurate
لذا كانوا قلقين من أن القصص لم تكن دقيقة تمامًا
as police were claiming them to be.
كما قالت الشرطة لهم.
And again, through social media, we started encountering
ومرة أخرى ومن خلال وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي بدأنا نواجه
individuals with material like this: photographs, evidence.
أفرادا بحوزتهم مواد مثل هذه: صور وأدله.
Now, this does not show the attack on Ian Tomlinson,
الآن، هذا لا يُظهر الهجوم على (ايان توميسون)،
but he appears to be in some distress.
لكنه يبدو أنه في حالة حرجة.
Was he drunk? Did he fall over?
هل كان ثملاً؟ هل وقع على الأرض؟
Did this have anything to do with the police officers next to him?
هل لهذا علاقة بضباط الشرطة الذي كان بجانبه؟
Here he appears to be talking to them.
هنا يبدو أنه يتحدث معهم.
For us, this was enough to investigate further, to dig deeper.
بالنسبة لنا ، كان هذا كافيًا لإجراء المزيد من البحث، والتعمق أكثر.
The result was putting out stories ourselves.
كانت النتيجة هو نشر القصص بأنفسنا.
One of the most amazing things about the internet is:
أحد أكثر الأشياء المدهشة حول الإنترنت هو:
the information that people put out is freely available to anyone,
المعلومات التي يطرحها الناس تصبح متاحة للجميع،
as we all know.
كما نعلم جميعًا.
That doesn't just go for citizen journalists,
هذا لا ينطبق فقط على للصحفيين المواطنين،
or for people putting out messages on Facebook or Twitter.
أو الأشخاص الذين يضعون رسائل على فيسبوك وتويتر.
That goes for journalists themselves,
هذا ينطبق على الصحفيين أنفسهم،
people like me.
الناس الذين هم مثلي.
As long as your news is the right side of a paywall, i.e, it's free,
طالما أن أخبارك صحيحة ومجانية،
anybody can access it.
يمكن لأي شخص الوصول إليها.
And stories like these,
وقصص مثل هذه،
which were questioning the official version of events,
التي كان تناقش الروايات الرسمية للأحداث،
which were skeptical in tone,
التي كانت مرتبكة في لهجتها،
allowed people to realize that we had questions ourselves.
سمحت للناس أن يدركوا أن لديهم أسئلة خاصة بهم.
They were online magnets.
هم بمثابة مغناطيس في الإنترنت.
Individuals with material that could help us were drawn toward us
الأفراد الذين لديهم مواد بإمكانها مساعدتنا كانوا ينجذبون إلينا
by some kind of gravitational force.
من قبل نوع من قوة الجاذبية.
And after six days, we had managed to track down around 20 witnesses.
وبعد ستة أيام، تمكنا من العثور على حوالي 20 شاهداً.
We've plotted them here on the map.
قمنا بوضع أماكن تواجدهم على الخريطة.
This is the scene of Ian Tomlinson's death,
هذا هو مشهد موت (ايان توميسون)،
the Bank of England in London.
بنك إنجلترا في لندن.
And each of these witnesses that we plotted on the map,
وكل واحد من هؤلاء الشهود المشار لهم على الخريطة،
you could click on these small bullet points,
يمكنك الضغط على هذه النقاط الصغيرة،
and you could hear what they had to say,
ويمكنك سماع ما قالوه،
see their photographic image
ومشاهدة صورهم الفوتوغرافية
and at times, see their videographic images as well.
وفي بعض الأحيان، مشاهدة مقاطع الفيديو الخاصة بهم كذلك.
But still, at this stage,
لكن لا يزال، في هذه المرحلة،
with witnesses telling us that they'd seen police attack Ian Tomlinson
بالرغم من الشهود يقولون لنا أنهم شاهدوا هجوم الشرطة على (ايان توميسون)
before his death,
قبل موته.
still, police refused to accept that.
لا تزال الشرطة ترفض القبول بذلك.
There was no official investigation into his death.
لم يكن هناك تحقيق رسمي في وفاته.
And then something changed.
ثم تغير شيء ما.
I got an email from an investment fund manager in New York.
تلقيت بريدًا إلكترونيًا من أحد مدراء صناديق الاستثمار في نيويورك.
On the day of Ian Tomlinson's death, he'd been in London on business,
وكان هذا المدير في لندن للعمل، في نفس يوم وفاة (ايان توميسون)،
and he'd taken out his digital camera,
وأخرج كاميرته الرقمية،
and he'd recorded this.
وتمكن من تسجيل هذا الفيديو.
(Video) Narrator: This is the crowd at G20 protest
المذيع: هذا هو الحشد في احتجاج مجموعة العشرين
on April the 1st, around 7:20pm.
في الأول من أبريل حوالي الساعة 7:20 مساءً.
They were on Cornhill, near the Bank of England.
كانوا في كورنهيل، بالقرب من بنك إنجلترا.
This footage will form the basis of a police investigation
ستشكل هذه اللقطات أساس تحقيق الشرطة
into the death of this man.
في موت هذا الرجل.
Ian Tomlinson was walking through this area,
كان (ايان توميسون) يسير في هذه المنطقة،
attempting to get home from work.
يحاول العودة لمنزله بعد العمل.
(People yelling)
(أناس يصرخون)
We've slowed down the footage to show how it poses serious questions
قمنا بإبطاء اللقطات لأنها تطرح أسئلة مهمة
about police conduct.
حول سلوك الشرطة.
Ian Tomlinson had his back to riot officers and dog handlers
وكان (ايان توميسون) ظهره باتجاه ضباط مكافحة الشغب ومدربي الكلاب
and was walking away from them.
وكان يسير بعيدا عنهم.
He had his hands in his pockets.
كانت يديه في جيبه.
Here the riot officer appears to strike Tomlinson's leg area with a baton.
هنا يبدو أن ضابط مكافحة الشغب ضرب ساق توميسون بالعصا.
He then lunges at Tomlinson from behind.
ثم ينقض على توميسون من الخلف.
Tomlinson is propelled forward and hits the floor.
النتيجة اندفاع تومسيون للأمام والسقوط على الأرض.
(People yelling)
(الناس يصرخون)
Paul Lewis: OK. So, shocking stuff.
المتحدث: حسناً، هذه أشياء صادمة.
That video wasn't playing too well,
هذا الفيديو لم يكن بجودة جيدة،
but I remember when I first watched the video for myself,
لكن أتذكر عندما شاهدت الفيديو لأول مرة بنفسي،
I'd been in touch with this investment fund manager in New York,
كنت على اتصال مع مدير صندوق الاستثمار هذا في نيويورك،
and I had become obsessed with this story.
أصبحت مهووسًا بهذه القصة.
I had spoken to so many people who said they had seen this happen,
لقد تحدثت مع العديد من الأشخاص الذين قالوا إنهم شاهدوا هذا يحدث،
and the guy on the other end of the phone was saying,
والرجل على الطرف الآخر من الهاتف كان يقول،
"Look, the video shows it."
"انظر، يظهر الفيديو ذلك."
I didn't want to believe him until I saw it for myself.
لم أرد أن أصدقه حتى رأيت ذلك بنفسي.
It was two o'clock in the morning, I was there with an IT guy --
كانت الساعة الثانية صباحًا كنت مع أحد رجال تقنية المعلومات
the video wasn't coming.
لم يكن هذا الفيديو قادمًا
Finally, it landed, and I clicked on it.
أخيرا، وصل وقمت بتشغيله.
And I realized: this is really something quite significant.
وأدركت: هذا حقا شيء مهم جدًا.
Within 15 hours, we put it on our website.
في غضون 15 ساعة، وضعنا الفيديو على موقعنا.
The first thing police did was they came to our office --
أول شيء فعلته الشرطة هو أنهم جاؤوا إلى مكتبنا
senior officers came to our office --
جاء كبار الضباط إلى مكتبنا
and asked us to take the video down.
طلبوا إزالة الفيديو وحذفه من موقعنا.
We said no.
رفضنا ذلك.
It would have been too late, anyway,
كان سيكون قد فات الأوان على أي حال،
because it had traveled around the world.
لأن المقطع انتشر حول العالم.
And the officer in that film, in two days' time,
والضابط الذي ظهر في ذلك الفيلم وفي غضون يومين،
will appear before an inquest jury in London,
سيظهر أمام هيئة استجواب في لندن،
and they have the power to decide that Ian Tomlinson was unlawfully killed.
ولديهم القدرة لإقرار أن كان (ايان توميسون) قد قُتل بطريقة غير مشروعة.
So that's the first case; I said two cases today.
هذه هي القضية الأولى، ذكرت توجد قضيتان اليوم.
The second case is this man.
القضية الثانية هي هذا الرجل.
Now, like Ian Tomlinson, he was a father, he lived in London.
مثل (ايان توميسون) كان هذا الرجل أبا ويعيش في لندن.
But he was a political refugee from Angola.
ولكنه كان لاجئا سياسيا من أنغولا.
And six months ago, the British government decided
وقد قررت الحكومة البريطانية قبل ستة أشهر
they wanted to return him to Angola;
أنه سيتم إرجاعه لأنغولا،
he was a failed asylum seeker.
حيث فشل طلبه للجوء.
So they booked him a seat on an airline, a flight from Heathrow.
لذا قاموا بشراء تذكرة له على إحدى الطائرات من هيثرو.
Now, the official version of events, the official explanation,
الرواية الرسمية للأحداث والتفسير الرسمي
of Jimmy Mubenga's death
لوفاة (جيمي موبينغا)
was simply that he'd taken ill.
أنه أصيب بمرض ما.
He'd become unwell on the flight, the plane had returned to Heathrow,
حيث تدهورت حالته أثناء الطيران، واضطرت الطائرة للرجوع لهيثرو،
and then he was transferred to hospital and pronounced dead.
ومن ثم تم نقله للمستشفى وتم إعلان وفاته لاحقًا.
Now, what actually happened to Jimmy Mubenga,
ما حدث في الحقيقة ل (جيمي موبينغا)،
the story we were able to tell, my colleague Mathew Taylor and I,
والقصة التي تمكنا من روايتها، زميلي (ماثيو تايلر) وأنا،
was that, actually, three security guards began trying to restrain him
هي أن ثلاثة من رجال الأمن بدأوا محاولة تكبيله
in his seat;
في كرسيه،
when was resisting his deportation, they were restraining him in his seat.
حيث أنه كان يقاوم عملية ترحيله، فحاولوا أن يكبلوه لكرسيه.
They placed him in a dangerous hold.
وقاموا بإمساكه بطريقة خطيرة.
It keeps detainees quiet, and he was making a lot of noise.
الطريقة هي لإبقاء المعتقلين هادئين، وكان هو يصدر الكثير من الأصوات.
But it can also lead to positional asphyxia,
ولكنها يمكن أن تؤدي أيضًا للاختناق الموضعي،
a form of suffocation.
شكل من أشكال الاختناق.
So you have to imagine: there were other passengers on the plane,
يمكنكم أن تتصوروا: وجود مسافرين آخرين على متن الطائرة،
and they could hear him saying,
ويمكنهم سماعه وهو يقول
"I can't breathe! I can't breathe! They're killing me!"
"لا يمكنني التنفس!، لا يمكنني التنفس! إنهم يقتلونني!"
And then he stopped breathing.
ومن ثم توقف عن التنفس.
So how did we find these passengers?
إذا كيف عثرنا على هؤلاء المسافرين؟
In the case of Ian Tomlinson, the witnesses were still in London.
في قضية (ايان تومسيون)، كان الشهود ما زالوا في لندن.
But these passengers, many of them, had returned to Angola.
إلا أن معظم هؤلاء المسافرين، رجعوا لأنغولا.
How were we going to find them?
كيف سنقدر أن نعثر عليهم؟
Again, we turned to the internet.
مجددًا، لجأنا للإنترنت.
We wrote, as I said before, stories -- they're online magnets.
كما قلنا سابقا، كتبنا قصص كانت بمثابة مغناطيس على الإنترنت.
The tone of some these stories, journalism professors might frown upon
لهجة بعض هذه القصص قد تثير امتعاض أساتذة الصحافة
because they were skeptical;
لأن كان طابعها الشك،
they were asking questions, perhaps speculative,
كانت تطرح أسئلة، وربما تتنبأ،
maybe the kind of things journalists shouldn't do.
وهي أشياء يجب على الصحافيين تجنبها.
But we needed to do it, and we needed to use Twitter also.
لكن كان يجب علينا القيام بها، كما كان يجب علينا اللجوء لتويتر.
Here I'm saying an Angolan man dies on a flight.
أقول هنا أن رجل من أنغولا لقي حتفه على متن طائرة
This story could be big; a level of speculation.
يمكن أن تكون القصة كبيرة، على مستوى من التخمين.
This next tweet says, "Please RT."
التغريدة التالية تحتوي على "Please RT"
That means "please retweet," please pass down the chain.
وهي تعني "إعادة إرسال" الرجاء الإرسال للمزيد من الناس.
And one of the fascinating things about Twitter
وأحد الأشياء المدهشة المتعلقة بتويتر
is that the pattern of flow of information
هو أن نمط تدفق المعلومات
is unlike anything we've ever seen before.
لا يشبه أي شيء قد رأيته في السابق.
We don't really understand it,
نحن في الواقع لا نفهم ما يجري،
but once you let go of a piece of information,
ولكن بمجرد أن تنشر معلومة ما،
it travels like wind.
فإنها تنتشر كالرياح.
You can't determine where it ends up.
لا يمكنك التحكم بالمدى الذي قد تصل إليه.
But strangely,
إلا أن الغريب،
tweets have an uncanny ability to reach their intended destination.
للتغريدات قدرة غريبة للوصول للجهات التي نريد أن تصل لها.
And in this case, it was this man.
وفي هذه الحالة، أردنا هذا الرجل.
He says, "I was also there on the BA77" -- that's the flight number --
يقول "كنت أيضا على الرحلة BA77" هذا كان رقم الرحلة
"And the man was begging for help,
"وكان الرجل يتوسل المساعدة،
and I now feel so guilty that I did nothing."
والآن أشعر بذنب كبير، لأنني لم أفعل شيئا"
This was Michael.
كان ذاك مايكل.
He was on an Angolan oil field when he sent me this tweet.
عندما أرسل هذه التغريدة، كان يوجد في حقل للنفط في أنغولا.
I was in my office in London.
وأنا كنت في مكتبي في لندن.
He had concerns about what happened on the flight.
وكانت لديه شكوك حول ما جرى على الطائرة.
He'd gone onto his laptop, he typed in the flight number.
استخدم حاسوبه المحمول للبحث عن رقم الرحلة.
He had encountered that tweet, he had encountered our stories.
ومن ثم وجد على التغريدة التي أرسلناها، وبعدها عثر على تحقيقاتنا.
He realized we had an intention to tell a different version of events;
أدرك أننا ننوي قول رواية مختلفة لما جرى،
we were skeptical.
أننا كنا متشككين.
And he contacted me.
عندها تواصل معي.
And this is what Michael said.
وهذا ما قاله مايكل.
(Audio) Michael: I'm pretty sure it'll turn out to be asphyxiation.
(صوت مايكل): أنا متأكد أن الأمر سيتضح أنه كان اختناق.
The last thing we heard the man saying was he couldn't breathe.
آخر ما سمعنا ما قاله الرجل كان لا أستطيع أن أتنفس.
And you've got three security guards,
وكان يوجد ثلاثة من عناصر الأمن،
each one of them looked like 100-kilo plus,
كان وزن كل منهم أكثر من 100 كيلوجرام على أقل تقدير،
bearing down on him, holding him down -- from what I could see,
كانوا يتكالبون عليه، يدفعونه للأسفل، وحسب ما رأيت،
below the seats.
أسفل المقاعد.
What I saw was the three men trying to pull him down below the seats.
ما رأيته أن الرجال الثلاثة كانوا يحاولون دفعه أسفل المقاعد.
And all I could see was his head sticking up above the seats,
واستطعنا رؤية رأسه فقط الظاهر فوق المقاعد،
and he was hollering out, you know, "Help me!"
وكان يصرخ "انجدوني!"
He just kept saying, "Help me! Help me!"
استمر بقول "انجدوني! انجدوني!"
And then he disappeared below the seats.
ومن ثم اختفى تحت المقاعد.
And you could see the three security guards sitting on top of him from there.
وبإمكانك رؤية رجال الأمن الثلاثة يجلسون فوقه بعد ذاك.
For the rest of my life,
لبقية حياتي،
I'm always going to have that in the back of my mind.
سيبقى ذاك الموقف يجول في خاطري.
Could I have done something?
هل كان بإمكاني فعل شيء؟
That's going to bother me every time I lay down to go to sleep now.
سيبقى هذا ينغص علي في كل مرة أخلد للنوم.
Wow; I didn't get involved
يا الهي، لم أتدخل
because I was scared I might get kicked off the flight and lose my job.
لأنني كنت أخشى أن أطرد من الطائرة وأخسر عملي.
If it takes three men to hold a man down,
إن تطلب الأمر ثلاثة رجال لتثبيت رجل واحد،
to put him on a flight,
لوضعه على متن رحلة،
one the public is on,
وعلى مرأى من العامة،
that's excessive.
فهذا إفراط للقوة.
OK?
حسنًا؟
If the man died,
إن توفى الرجل،
that right there is excessive.
فإن هذا بحد ذاته إفراط.
PL: So that was his interpretation of what had happened on the flight.
بول: كانت هذه رواية مايكل لما حدث على متن تلك الرحلة.
And Michael was actually one of five witnesses
في الحقيقة، مايكل هو أحد خمسة شهود
that we eventually managed to track down, most of them, as I said,
الذين تمكنا من التوصل لهم، وأغلبهم كما قلت،
through the internet, through social media.
من خلال الإنترنت ومن خلال وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي.
We could actually place them on the plane,
تمكنا من تحديد أماكن جلوسهم على الطائرة،
so you could see exactly where they were sat.
لذا يمكنكم رؤية أماكن مقاعدهم.
And I should say at this stage
ويجب أن أقول على هذا المسرح
that one really important dimension to all of this
أن الدافع أساسي ومهم لهذا كله
for journalists who utilize social media
للصحفيين الذين يستخدمون وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي
and who utilize citizen journalism
ويستخدمون صحافة المواطنين
is making sure we get our facts correct.
هو أن نحصل على الحقائق كما وقعت.
Verification is absolutely essential.
التحقق هو عامل هام للغاية.
So in the case of the Ian Tomlinson witnesses,
لذا في حالة شهود (ايان توميسون)،
I got them to return to the scene of the death
طلبت منهم الرجوع للمكان الذي وقعت به الوفاة
and physically walk me through
وأن يمشوا معي شخصيا
and tell me exactly what they had seen.
ويرووا لي ما رأوه بالضبط.
That was absolutely essential.
هذا أمر هام للغاية.
In the case of Mubenga, we couldn't do that,
لم نتمكن من فعل هذا في قضية (موبينغا)،
but they could send us their boarding passes.
لكن استطاعوا أن يرسلوا بطاقات الصعود للطائرة.
And we could interrogate what they were saying
وتحققنا مما كانوا يقولونه لنا
and ensure it was consistent with what other passengers were saying, too.
لكي نتأكد من توافقه مع ما رواه المسافرون الآخرون أيضا.
The danger in all of this for journalists -- for all of us --
الخطر الكامن في هذا الأمر لنا جميعا وخصوصا الصحفيين،
is that we're victims of hoaxes,
أننا يمكن أن نكون ضحية خداع،
or that there's deliberate misinformation fed into the public domain.
أو يتم نشر معلومات مضللة ويتم تداولها بين العامة.
So we have to be careful.
لذا يجب أن نلتزم بالحذر.
But nobody can deny the power of citizen journalism.
إلا أنه لا يمكن لأحد إنكار قوة صحافة المواطنين.
When a plane crashes into the Hudson two years ago,
عندما هبطت طائرة اضطراريا على نهر الهدسون قبل سنتين،
and the world finds out about this because a man is on a nearby ferry,
فقد قام شخص على عبارة مجاورة بنقل الخبر للعالم،
and he takes out his iPhone and photographs the image of the plane
حيث التقط صور الطائرة على هاتفه
and sends it around the world --
وأرسلها لجميع أنحاء الأرض
that's how most people found out initially,
هكذا علم الناس عن الأمر في البداية،
in the early minutes and hours, about the plane in the Hudson River.
في الدقائق والساعات الأولى لتواجد الطائرة على الهدسون.
Now, think of the two biggest news stories of the year.
فكروا الآن في أكبر قصتين حدثتا خلال العام الحالي.
We had the Japanese earthquake and the tsunami.
حدث الزلزال في اليابان وحدثت موجة تسونامي.
Cast your mind's eye back to the images that you saw
عودوا بذاكرتكم للصور التي رأيتموها
on your television screens.
على شاشات تلفازكم.
They were boats left five miles inland.
سفن جرفت مسافة 5 أميال داخل اليابسة.
They were houses being moved along,
كما تم تجريف منازل من أماكنها،
as if in the sea.
كما لو أنها بنيت على البحر.
Water lifting up inside people's living rooms, supermarkets shaking --
الماء يرتفع داخل غرف المعيشة، متاجر تهتز...
these were images shot by citizen journalists
كل هذه كانت صور صورها صحفيون مواطنون
and instantly shared on the internet.
وتم نشرها فورا على الإنترنت.
And the other big story of the year: the political crisis,
قصة أخرى كبيرة حدث خلال السنة، وهي الأزمة السياسية،
the political earthquake in the Middle East.
الزلزال السياسي في الشرق الأوسط.
And it doesn't matter if it was Egypt or Libya or Syria or Yemen.
ونحن نتكلم بشكل عام عن مصر وليبيا وسوريا واليمن.
Individuals have managed to overcome the repressive restrictions
تمكن الناس من التغلب على القيود القمعية
in those regimes
لتلك الأنظمة
by recording their environment
من خلال تسجيل ما يحدث في محيطهم
and telling their own stories on the internet.
ومن ثم ينشرون قصصهم على الإنترنت.
Again, always very difficult to verify,
ومرة أخرى، من الصعب التحقق من صحتها،
but potentially, a huge layer of accountability.
ولكنها تحمل قدر كبير من المسؤولية.
This image -- and I could have shown you any, actually;
هذه الصورة، بمقدوري اختيار أي صورة أخرى كذلك،
YouTube is full of them --
يوتيوب مليء بها،
This image is of an apparently unarmed protester in Bahrain.
هذه الصورة لمتظاهر أعزل في البحرين.
And he's being shot by security forces.
ويتم اطلاق النار عليه من قبل قوات الأمن.
It doesn't matter if the individual being mistreated,
ليس من المهم أن تمت إساءة التعامل مع الشخص،
possibly even killed,
أو حتى تم قتله،
is in Bahrain or in London.
في البحرين أو لندن.
But citizen journalism and this technology has inserted
إلا أن كلا من صحافة المواطنين وهذه التكنولوجيا أضافت
a new layer of accountability into our world,
حسا من المساءلة للعالم،
and I think that's a good thing.
وأعتقد أن هذا أمر جيد.
So to conclude: the theme of the conference, "Why not?" --
في النهاية، موضوع المؤتمر هو "لم لا؟"
I think for journalists, it's quite simple, really.
في الحقيقة، أعتقد أن الأمر بسيط بالنسبة للصحفي.
I mean, why not utilize this technology,
أعني، لماذا لا نستخدم هذه التكنولوجيا،
which massively broadens the boundaries of what's possible,
وهي تعمل على توسيع نطاق حدود ما يمكن انجازه،
accept that many of the things that happen in our world now go recorded,
نتقبل أن معظم ما يحدث الآن في عالمنا يتم تسجيله،
and we can obtain that information
ويمكن الحصول على هذه المعلومات من خلال
through social media?
وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي؟
That's new for journalists.
هذا أمر جديد للصحفيين.
The stories I showed you, I don't think we would have been able to investigate
لا أعتقد أننا كنا سنتمكن من التحقيق في القصص التي عرضتها لكم
10 years ago, possibly even five years ago.
قبل عشرة سنوات، أو حتى خمس سنوات.
I think there's a very good argument to say that the two deaths,
أعتقد أنه يمكننا أن نناقش حالتي الوفاة،
the death of Ian Tomlinson and the death of Jimmy Mubenga,
وفاة "ايان توميلسون" ووفاة "جيمي موبينغا"،
we still today wouldn't know exactly what had happened in those cases.
ما زلنا غير متأكدين تماما مما حدث إلى اليوم.
And "Why not?" for people like yourselves?
وبالنسبة لأشخاص مثلكم ف"لما لا؟"
Well, I think that's very simple, too.
أعتقد أن الأمر بسيط للغاية أيضا.
If you encounter something that you believe is problematic,
إن واجهت أمرًا ما تعتقد أنه يسبب مشكلة ما،
that disturbs you, that concerns you, an injustice of some kind,
أمر يزعجك، أو أمر يهمك، أو ظلم من نوع ما،
something that just doesn't feel quite right,
أمر يشعرك أن هناك خطب ما،
then why not witness it, record it and share it?
إذا ما المانع من أن تشاهده، وتسجله، وتشاركه؟
That process of witnessing, recording and sharing is journalism.
عملية المشاهدة والتسجيل والمشاركة تعتبر صحافة.
And we can all do it. Thank you.
ويمكننا جميعا أن نقوم بذلك. شكرًا جزيلًا.